你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎继续参加pwn学院的沙盒课程
welcome to the continuation of the sandboxing module of pwn College
我是Yan
I'm Yan
今天我们要讲的是seccomp
and today we're going to be talking about seccomp
什么是seccomp
what is seccomp
seccomp本质上是Linux的系统调用防火墙
seccomp is essentially a system call firewall for Linux
Seccomp是一组相当复杂的功能
seccomp is a fairly complicated set of functionality
可以让有安全意识的开发人员
that can allow a developer that is security conscious
试图将应用程序用沙盒隔离
and is attempting to sandbox  application
防止应用被黑后做坏事
to keep it from doing bad things in the case that it gets hacked
写复杂的规则
um to write complex rules
禁用某些系统调用
to disable certain system calls
允许某些系统调用
to allow certain system calls um
甚至是基于它们的参数来过滤系统调用
to filter um system calls even based on their argument variables
调整系统调用
um to tweak system calls
比如这个系统调用应该在这个条件直接返回这个值
uh to say that you know this call under this condition should just return this value
这些类似的
something along these lines
这些都是系统调用
again these are system calls
而不是程序中的一般函数调用
not general function calls in the program
系统调用是与系统交互
but system calls interacting with the environment
Seccomp很强大
seccomp is powerful
它能遗传给子进程
it is inherited by children
它甚至能限制root用户运行的进程
it is able to restrict processes even run by root
还有很多其他的能力
um with a lot of other capabilities and so forth
这基本是现代沙盒中最大的部分
um it is the uh kind of biggest part of a modern sandbox
嗯
um
比如Chrome沙盒等等
something like the Chrome sandbox and and uh so forth um
如果你感兴趣，你可以看看seccomp的文档
if you're interested you can look at the documentation for seccomp
规则可以写得非常非常复杂
the rules can get very very complex
这是一项很牛的技术
it's a very cool piece of technology
让我们快速看一个例子
and let's take a quick look at an example
这有一个程序，一会会使用seccomp
so we have a program that will be seccomp soon
执行系统调用的程序
a program that does an execve system Call
execl是一个C包装器，它设置execve系统调用并调用它
precisely execl is a C wrapper that sets up the execve system call and calls it
我们会用参数调用/bin/cat
and we're gonna call /bin/cat with the arguments
Arg[0]是cat Arg[1]是/flag
arg[0] is cat arg[1] is /flag
参数0
of course argue zero is
通常是你输入到shell里要启动的程序
you know typically the the the what you enter as to invoke the process into your shell
参数一是第一个参数
argue one is the first argument
如果我手动运行这个，它就是cat会输出的东西
and that's what cat will cat out if I run this manually
这是我在系统上放的一个用于演示的flag
here's a flag I put on my system for demonstration
当然，如果我编译它
and of course if I compile this
运行它
and I run it
效果很好
it works great
成功接收到了flag
flag received
好吧
alright
现在为了让它更安全，引入了一个沙盒
now let's make this more secure so I have a sandbox
我插入这4行，这就行了
and I inserted these 4 lines this is all it takes
非常简单
it's very simple
这就是使用一个沙盒需要的全部了
this is all it takes to build in a sandbox into your process
让我们一行一行的过一下
let's go through the lines one by one
1我们创建一个seccomp filter
one we created a seccomp filter data structure
2我们用默认策略初始化它
2 we initialized it with a default policy
这里写着SCMP_ACT_ALLOW，就这么简单
this says seccomp action allows that simple
它允许在默认情况下调用每个系统，除非我们另有说明
it just allows every system called by default unless we say otherwise
下一行我们就说了，
and here the next line we say otherwise we say okay
添加到这个我们正在建立的seccomp过滤器
add to this seccomp filter that we're building
一个kill动作
with an action of kill
系统调用execve
the system call execve
所以任何时候
so anytime
当然，之后你可以给值添加额外的检查，等等，但是这里说
and then of course later on you can add additional checks onto the values and so forth but this says
任何时候调用execve就
anytime execve is called
终止程序
kill the program
所以这样就将execve隔离开了
so this sandboxes execve away
酷
cool
所以,嗯
so um
第四行使用这个过滤器
the 4th line of course applies this filter
它将其加载到内核中
it loads this into the kernel
做一大堆事情
does a whole bunch of stuff
这些库调用在底层执行很多其他的系统调用
these are library calls that do other crazy system calls underneath
确保我们的沙盒安全
and secure our sandbox
好的
alright
现在让我们编译这个新文件
let's now compile this new one
这不会成功，因为我们需要链接在一个seccomp库
this won't work because we need to link in a the seccomp library
这样就行了，顺便说一下
and this work by the by the way and
为了安装seccomp库，您需要这样做
in order to install the seccomp library you need to do something like this
这个我已经做过了
which I really did
否则你将无法编译它
otherwise you won't be able to compile this alright
现在我们有了新的和改进的
now we have our new and improved
作为提醒
just as reminder
这是我们要运行的程序
this is the program we're about to run
它会seccomp掉execve然后运行execve
and it's gonna seccomp away execve and then run execve
如果我们现在运行这个程序
and if we run this program now
它报系统调用错误
it says bad system call
运气不好
no luck right
我们用strace看看发生了什么
let's see what happens with an strace
不管strace输出什么
whatever the strace is
如果我们在这里找找
if we scroll up in our program
我们看到程序调用了多个系统调用来设置seccomp
we see that the program calls several different system calls to set up the seccomp
重要的一个是
the important one
所有这些都很重要
all of these are important
所以我建议查资料看看，比如这个
and I recommend you read up on what this does for example
这将停止已隔离的程序
this specifically stops a program that has been seccomped
或
from or
它使得当一个程序被seccomp
it makes it so that when a program that has been seccomp
例如，执行一个SUID程序
executes for example a set UID program
由于与LD_PRELOAD相似的原因，SUID特权不会生效
the set UID privileges don't apply for reasons  that are very very similar to LD_PRELOAD with set UID programs
seccomp的功能主要看过滤器配置了什么
this seccomp ah is what applies the filter right and
这是创建的过滤器的内存地址
and ah this is the location of our filter that we created in memory and so forth
接下来是当我们执行execve时
and the further thing is when we do the execve
我们马上就会被SIGSYS干掉
we immediately get killed by SIGSYS
SIGSYS是一种信号
SIGSYS is um a signal specifically
是31号信号
it is signal 31
我们当然可以创建一个信号处理器来处理信号31
we could of course create a signal handler to handle signal 31 and do stuff
但是你也可以设置seccomp，这样它就会杀死你的进程
but you can also set up seccomp so that it just kill dash 9 your process
当您触发一个不应该触发的系统调用时
when you trigger a system call that you're not supposed to
这就是seccomp的基本原理
and that is basically how seccomp works
还有一件事要讲，seccomp将由子进程继承
one more thing let me show you that seccomp will be inherited by the child
如果我们执行strace cat /flag
so if we strace cat /flag
我们能看到它从文件中读入了flag
we see that it reads in the flag from the file
我们可以对read系统调用进行seccomp
we can actually seccomp with  read
这个程序实际上不会调用read，但是cat会
so this program doesn't actually get read but cat does
因为cat是这个程序的子程序
and since cat is a child of this program
我们会打断cat的执行
we will break cat
让我们编译它，运行它
let's compile this let's run it
没输出flag，错误的系统调用。用strace看一下
no cat, bad system call. let's strace it
如果你向上滚动，可以看到cat运行了
and here this is cat now running right if you scroll up
这里的是seccomp的执行痕迹
somewhere here's the seccomp
这里是execve cat，它执行成功了
here's the execve cat and it worked
cat进程启动了
this is cat running now
这里cat尝试调用read
and this is cat trying to read
和被
and being
哦，它还在初始化
oh it's cat still initializing
尝试读入libc库
trying to read in libc
加载器在读入libc
the loader reading libc
然后这里进程就被kill掉了
and that kills the process
非常令人兴奋的东西
pretty exciting stuff
让我们来看看其中的含义
let's move on to the implications
实际上，首先让我们看看seccomp的原理
actually first let's move on to how the seccomp work
这是一个很有趣的功能，可以在内核中实现很多很酷的东西
that's a very interesting piece of a functionality that enables a lot of cool stuff in the kernel and so forth
或者说很酷的安全功能
or rather cool stuff in terms of security
seccomp使用了名为扩展伯克利包过滤器的内核功能
seccomp works through a kernel functionality called Extended Berkeley Packet Filters
bpf实际上是一个架构，它是一个虚拟架构
B P F is actually an architecture it is a virtual architecture
不像我了解的硬件BPF执行程序，还没被广泛运用
that aren't like hardware BPF executors that I know over that aren't wide scale use
但在内核内有一个虚拟机，可以说是BPF的模拟器
but inside the kernel there's a virtual machine like an emulator for BPF
它会执行这些过滤器
that executes these filters
这些过滤器是由，比如seccomp库，建立的
that are built up by for example those seccomp library calls
我们调用这些库调用，他们建立了这个EBPF过滤器程序
that we call those those library calls that built up this EBPF filter program
它被加载到内核中
that is loaded into the kernel
当内核接收到用户进程的调用时，它会过滤系统调用的参数
and runs to filter system call arguments when the kernel receives a system call from user process
它们也被用在其他地方
they're also used in other places
它们最初是被iptables用来过滤网络流量的
they're originally created to filter um net traffic with iptables
而且
and
从那时起
since then
它们被用来过滤参数
they've been obviously used to filter arguments
系统调用参数
system call arguments
它们也被用来实现一些非常不可思议的事情
they've also been um used to enable some pretty incredible
比如对操作系统执行过程的深度追踪
in depths tracing of a of a system
如果你喜欢捣鼓操作系统
if you're interested in playing around with your os
看看这个链接
um check out this link
里面有一大堆使用eBPF的非常棒的实用程序
it's a whole bunch of really awesome utilities that use extended Berkeley Packet Filters
以及一个叫做K探针的内核功能
along with a kernel functionality called K Probe
它能hook到内核里和一些非常有趣的地方
to basically hook into the kernel and a bunch of uh really interesting places
得到很多有趣的数据
to get a lot of interesting data out
你可以做到，比如跟踪机器上每个进程的每个系统调用
you can do stuff like trace every system call made by every single process on your machine
并告诉进程什么时候打开某些文件
and tell when uh processes are opening certain files
你可以用这个来发现
uh you can um use this to profile and
理解何时函数运行效率低，还能用来探索各种深奥的东西
understand when functions are running slowly when you know all sorts of awesome stuff
看看那个链接
check out that link
它和这门课完全无关
it's completely irrelevant to this class
但是一套很有趣的工具
but it is a very interesting set of tools
Secomp只是EBPF的另一种应用
and Secomp is another application of EBPF
好了
all right
这就是Secomp的入门速成课程
that is the intro to Secomp a crash course
当然，如果你对更多的关于seccomp的东西感兴趣
if you are interested in more seccomp stuff of course
这里我有最简单的seccomp程序
here I had the minimum seccomp program
所有这些您都可以在手册页中查找
all of this you can look up man pages for
如果你对添加什么规则感兴趣
if you're interested in what rules you can add
哦
oops
使用man，你就能读到所有的东西
do man this and you can read all about it
你可以添加一大堆东西
you can add a lot of stuff
一大堆setcomp功能
a lot of functionality setcomp
在下一模块中
in the next module
抱歉，在下一个视频中
sorry in the next video
我们将讨论如何逃离这样的沙盒隔离
we're going to talk about how we can escape from such jails
到时见
see you then